你好黑客
hello hackers
我们看一下PWN学院内核模块的第三个视频
let's dive into the third video in the kernel module of pwn college
内核的模块
modules
今天我们要讲的是内核的模块
so we're going to talk today in this video about kernel modules
内核模块是Linux生态系统的重要组成部分
kernel modules are an important part of the Linux ecosystem let's say
它们是什么
what are they
它们基本上就是库
they are basically libraries
概念上类似于用户空间的库
conceptually analogous to a user space library
你可以将libc加载到进程中
so you might load libc into your process
以提供某些功能
to provide certain functionality
同样地
in a similar way
内核将内核模块加载到自身以提供功能
a kernel loads kernel modules into itself to provide functionality
内核模块是一个elf文件
kernel module is an elf file
它有一个不同的后缀名
it has a different extension
.ko而不是.so
.ko instead of .so
但它是一个elf文件
but it is an elf file
它也有段、节等等，就像elf文件一样
and it has segment sections etc just like an elf file
就像so库
and just like a shared object the library
但它会被加载到内核的地址空间
it is loaded into the address space of the kernel
类似于库会被加载到进程的地址空间
similar to how a library is loaded into the address space of a process
类似于库会以该进程的身份运行
and similar to how a library is running as that process
模块会以内核的身份运行
the module is running as the kernel
内核模块主要用于实现设备驱动程序
kernel modules are used to implement predominantly device drivers
如果你有显卡的话
if you have a graphics card
我有一个显卡
i have a graphics card
提前看一下
so i'll show you looking a little bit ahead
执行lsmod
do an lsmod
它列出了我系统上运行的模块
this lists the modules running on my system
我的nvidia显卡已经加载到内核中了
and i have my nvidia graphics cards loaded into my kernel
显卡模块驱动程序
graphic card modules drivers
这是一个内核驱动
so that's one thing that kernel drivers provide
文件系统
file systems
许多文件系统实现都在内核中
a lot of file system implementations are in the kernel
这样更快
it's faster that way
你可以用fuse在用户空间实现文件系统
you can implement file systems in user space using something called fuse
我希望那是一个模块
i was hoping that's a module
也许它编译进了
maybe that's compiled in
但我想我的文件系统已经编译进内核了
but i guess my file systems are compiled in
或者至少
or at least you know
我们接着讲
we'll move on from that
文件系统可以是动态加载的内核模块
file systems can be kernel modules loaded on the fly
网络功能
networking functionality
比如这里的防火墙
so for example my firewall here
是
is
或至少防火墙中的一些功能是内核模块
or at least some functionality in my firewall is a kernel module
还有很多其他的东西
and various other stuff
比如，CPU特性的硬件支持
hardware support for CPU features
加密之类的
for Crypto stuff like this
任何你只想在特定情况加载的功能
anything that you might want to load in certain circumstances
或者只想在某些系统加载的功能
or in certain systems but not others
都适用于做成内核模块
works well as a kernel module as a library
那么如何与这些模块交互呢
so how do you interact with these modules
显然我们会讨论
because obviously we're going to be talking about
你该如何与这些外加到内核的模块交互
how you interact with these additions to the kernel
最终利用里面的漏洞
exploit vulnerabilities eventually
当我们把所有的东西放在一起
when we start putting it all together
然后实现提权之类的
and then achieve privilege escalation or what have you
从历史上看
historically
有很多交互点
there's a number of interaction points
我们会讲到其中的一些
and we're gonna cover a bunch of them
其中一些是只有以前有的
some of them are historical
比如这个
like this one
曾经
historically
给内核模块，注册系统调用处理程序，并不难
it was not too difficult for a kernel module to register a syscall handler
因此，可能你加载一个内核模块
so you might suddenly load a kernel module
就有了一个新的系统调用，叫sysyan
suddenly have a new system call, called sysyan
你可以给sysyan传参数
and you could call sysyan with some arguments
然后该模块会收到
and then the module would receive that
会检测到该系统调用，执行它
would intercept that system call and do stuff
这在现代内核中显然是不支持的
this is very explicitly unsupported in modern kernels
内核开发人员想尽办法让这变得更加困难
kernel developers have gone out of their way to make this more difficult
它经常被rootkit利用
it was often used by root kits
用来覆盖open之类的
to overwrite the functionality for open and so forth
用来在系统中隐藏恶意软件
to hide malicious software on a system
让试图找它的合法用户，找不到
from legitimate users that were trying to find it
这不是
it's not really a
双方对抗了十多年了
fought over a decade now
这种内核模块使用方式已经不支持了
not a supported way of using kernel modules
内核模块也可以注册中断
a kernel module could also register interrupts
你可能还记得一些shellcode或沙盒逃逸中的题
so you might remember in some of the shellcoding or jailbreaking challenges
你用int指令
you use the int instruction
用中断，触发系统调用
interrupt to trigger system calls
这是最初的32位x86的系统调用方式
this was the 32 bit x86 way of doing system calls originally
在Linux中，它是int 0x80
and in Linux that's int 0x80
Int 128将跳转到内核
int 128 will jump into the kernel
然后进行系统调用
and do your system call
没人阻止你int 一个别的数
well nothing stop you from doing int other number
你可以做从0到255的任何事
you can do anything from you know 0 to 255
其中一些有语义含义
some of those have other semantic meanings
但举个例子
but for example
你可以为int 42指令创建一个钩子
you could create a hook for an int 42 instruction
你可以用LIDT或LGDT指令来创建它
and you could create it by using the LIDT or the LGDT instruction
将中断处理程序注册给CPU
to load an interrupt handler into the cpu
这样当int 42时
so when int 42 happens
处理程序
the handler
你模块中的函数的地址
that address of it within your module of a function
会被调用，来处理这个中断
will get called to handle that
这实际上是超级有助于魔改原有功能
this is actually super useful for retrofitting crazy functionality
例如，有两个中断
for example there are two interrupts that are
你可以用一个字节来触发
that you can trigger using one byte
当然int 0x80或int 0x42
of course int 0x80 or int 42
这是两字节的指令
that's two byte instruction
但int3和int1
but an int 3 and an int 1
实际上，int1好像不是实际的名字
actually i don't think the int 1 is the actual name
我记得指令的名字是icebp
i think it's ice is the name of the instruction
这些都是单字节指令
those are single byte instructions
你可以把它扔到任何地方去劫持某些功能
that you can just throw anywhere to hook certain functionality
举个例子
so for example
GDB将int3 0xcc插入到软件中，来设置断点
gdb inserts int 3 0xcc to set break points in software
但你可以创建一个模块
but you could create a module
改变int3的功能
that changes what int3 does
不像Linux内核的正常功能那样，引起SIGTRAP
instead of causing a SIGTRAP as is the normal functionality of the Linux kernel
Int3可以运行你自定义的代码
int3 could run your custom code
例如，记录函数跳转的位置
that for example records where functions are jumping
有一次我和一个朋友
i once with a friend of mine
写了一个内核模块
wrote a kernel module
结合自定义加载程序
where combined with a custom loader
把每个函数的开头替换为int 3
that would replace the beginning of every function with int 3
每一个函数的末尾都替换成int 1，或反过来
and the end of every function with int 1 or vice versa
基本上
would basically
记录了函数调用关系
keep track of what functions were calling each other
确保进程控制流不被劫持
and make sure that control flow didn't get hijacked
例如
for example
你可以做这样疯狂的事
you can do crazy stuff like that
你还可以做更疯狂的事情
you can also do even crazier stuff
比如劫持非法操作码的中断
like hook the interrupt that happens when you trigger invalid code
通常这会导致一个SIGILL被传到你的进程
usually that causes a SIGILL to be delivered to your process
你肯定已经在ROP或shellcode模块，头疼过了
as you'll i'm sure have painfully found out in the rop and shellcoding modules
但利用内核模块
but with a kernel module
你可以让它做任何事
you could make that do anything
我记得是6号中断
i think it's interrupt 6
不太确定
don't quote me on that
它是一个可劫持的中断
and you know it is a hookable interrupt and
它已经被安全研究员用于改造安全系统了
it has been used by security researchers to like retrofit security
实际上，我的一个学生
actually one of my students
你可以点击这个链接
you can click this link
看看他的研究视频
and go to his video of the research that he did
改进出更安全的read和write函数
to retrofit safer reads and writes
通过未定义指令
by using undefined instructions
利用未定义的指令在软件中创建它们
and abusing undefined instructions to basically create them in software
通常这是一个定制的交互方法
usually this is a bespoke interaction method
没人会把这样的模块作为产品发布
no one really ships production modules that do that
一种经常使用的交互方法
one interaction method that is used quite a lot
是文件
is files
所以最常见的与模块交互的方式
so the most common way in fact of interacting with modules
是模块创建一个文件
is that the module creates a file
或在文件系统的某处注册一个设备文件
or registers a device file somewhere on the file system
这个某处可以是/dev
and this somewhere can be /dev
这是创建设备文件的传统位置
this was the traditional place to create device files
如果你现在看看/dev
if you look at /dev right now
如果你查看Linux系统上的/dev
if you look at /dev on your Linux system
有很多东西
there's a lot of stuff
例如
for example
这个文件代表我硬盘
this is a file representing my hard drive
如果我是root的话，我可以打开它
and i can actually open it if i'm root
我有点害怕那样做
i'm a little afraid to do that
但我可以打开它
but i could open it
然后大量输出硬盘中的内容
and actually scream out my hard drive contents
比如可以用cat
using cat for example
就是普通的交互，它只是一个文件
just normal interaction it is just a file
cd-rom是我的光驱
cd rom is you know my cd drive
DVD驱动器，是的，这台电脑还有DVD驱动器
dvd drive and yes this computer has a dvd drive
等等
and so on
这里有很多不同的设备
so there's a lot of different devices here
能直接与内核模块通信
that talk directly to kernel modules
这很酷
which is pretty cool
还有/proc
there's also /proc
你用过/proc
you have played around with /proc
/proc也是
well /proc is also a place for
它最初是一个获取运行进程信息的地方
it started out as a place to get information about running processes
在Linux中
in Linux
它扩展成了内核模块交互的地方
it kind of expanded into this mess of kernel module interactions
很多内核模块等等
a lot of kernel modules and so forth
很多都被移到了/sys中
and a lot of that got moved into /sys
但内核模块中，你还能在/proc创建文件
but you can still create files in /proc from within kernel modules and
然后在用户空间与之交互
have user space interact with them
通过文件与模块交互
to interact with the module through a file
你只需调用open
you just call open
就是这么简单
that's it's that simple
你调用open
you call open
然后read，write，或一会儿讲的其它选择
and then either read write or i'll talk about alternatives later
你可以与这些模块进行交互
and you can interact with these modules
读写都很简单
read write very simple
在内核空间中
so in kernel space
你可以为，给模块注册的文件
you can register a read handler and a write handler
注册一个读处理程序和一个写处理程序
for the file that you register for your module
然后做一些常规操作
and then you can do stuff normal stuff
比如读入
like read in
这个读入有问题
that's a invalid read
马上
one sec
我修正一下
let me fix that
在用户空间中，你可以读这个文件
in userspace you can read from that file
这会让你内核模块处理程序被调用
and that will cause your kernel's handlers to be called and
这个读取请求会被你的
the read will be handled by your
抱歉
sorry
内核模块注册的处理程序处理
your kernel modules handler functions that you register in the module
这对处理一滴溜一滴溜数据的内核模块很有用
this is useful for modules that deal with like blobs of data
如麦克风
like a microphone
就比如有一个麦克风内核模块
so if you have a module for a microphone
或相机内核模块
or module for a camera
完了有人要读它
and someone starts reading from it
这个device_read/write就正管这种情况
that's exactly what this interface is for
有一个更高级的接口
there's a more advanced interface
叫io控制，ioctl
that uses what is called io control ioctl
ioctl是一个系统调用
ioctl is a system call
当然，这提供了一个更灵活的接口
of course that provides a much more flexible interface
稍等，我的硬件出了问题
one sec i'm having hardware problems this
我的鼠标坏了
my mouse just broke
不能推进幻灯片
so i can't advance a slide
好了
there we go okay
ioctl提供了一个灵活得多的接口
so ioctl provides a much more flexible interface
你注册一个ioctl处理程序
basically you register an ioctl handler
在用户空间中，你仍然可以像往常一样打开文件
and from user space you still open the file as normal
然后你调用ioctl
and you invoke an ioctl syscall
用上那个文件描述符
with that file descriptor
一个命令码
a command code
它是由内核模块定义并检查的
and this is a command code that's defined that's checked by the function in the kernel module
这是一个自定义命令码
so it's a custom command code
你可以发送任意数据
and you can send arbitrary data
这是非常灵活的
this is very flexible
也很危险
also very dangerous
这些数据在内核中很容易被错误处理
this data is very easy to mishandle in the kernel
造成了很多漏洞
causing a lot of vulnerabilities
许多漏洞都源于ioctl
a lot of vulnerabilities come from ioctl
源于一些糟糕的ioctl处理程序实现
like badly implemented ioctl handlers in kernel modules
该接口用于写入和读取非流式数据
this interface is useful for setting and retrieving non stream data
所以如果你有一个网络摄像头驱动程序
so if you have a webcam driver
你可能会流式的上传视频
you might stream out the video
就用read
using a just read you know
用read系统调用，和内核模块中的read处理程序
using a read syscall and the appropriate read handler in the kernel module
但你可能会检索和设置，分辨率、色彩平衡等选项
but you might retrieve and set options such as resolution color balance and so forth
就可以用ioctl
using ioctl as an example
一旦你触发了和内核的交互
so let's say once you trigger some interaction with the kernel
你打开文件
you open the file
向文件中写入内容
you write stuff into the file
读出数据，之类的
read from it or whatever
内核模块能做什么
what does the kernel module do
内核模块可以做任何事情
the kernel module can do anything
因为它运行在0环
because it is running in ring 0
但通常
but typically
内核模块很守规矩
kernel modules are fairly well behaved
通常它会从进程中读取一些内容
typically it'll read something from your process
比如，用ioctl，读取你提供的数据
for example using ioctl it will read that your provided data
我们一会儿会看copy_from_user和copy_to_user
and we'll look at copy_from_user and copy_to_user in a sec
它会做一些事情
it'll do stuff
它会打开文件
so it'll open files
读取文件
you know read from files
与硬件交互
interact with hardware
做各种驱动程序要做的事情
do all sorts of whatever it's driver stuff that it does
然后它用copy_to_user将数据写回用户空间
and then it'll write data back to user space using copy_to_user
在ioctl中很常见
again very common in ioctl
但read也是这么处理的
but also how read is handled
write是这么处理的
so this is how write would be handled
read是这么处理的
this is how read is handled
然后返回到用户空间
and then it returns to user space
很酷
very cool stuff
那么如何编译模块呢
so how do you compile modules
编译模块
you compile modules
你可以按照网上的指南去做
there's guides online you can follow
但我们为你创建了一个简单的环境，叫pwnkernel
but again we created a simple environment for you called pwnkernel
在pwncollege的github仓库中
under the pwn college GitHub organization
它很简单
it's very simple
现在我们在/pwn/kernel中
here we are in /pwn/kernel
进入src
if we go into src
这里有很多模块
i have a bunch of modules here
只需要运行build
you just run build
它会把它们都编译好
and it'll build all of them
部署到内核中
deploy them into the kernel
实际上这里错了
so actually this is incorrect
我改一下
let me fix that real quick
这是build.sh
it's build.sh
如果你想创建自己的内核模块
so if you want to create your own kernel module
受益于这里的PWN学院框架
benefiting from the pwn college framework here
你可以进入src
you're going to source
这是放着我们的内核模块
this is where our kernel modules live
还有一堆临时文件
there's a bunch of temporary files in here
你可以在这里创建
but you can create
这是最简单的，我一会儿给你们看
this is the simplest one i'll show it to you in a sec
然后创建，比如yanmodule.c
and create hello let's say yanmodule.c
编辑makefile
you edit the makefile
然后在这里添加yanmodule.o
and just add yanmodule.o here
我不知道为什么是.o
i don't know why .o for this
但你就这么做吧
but just do it
就是这么简单
and it's that simple
然后执行build
then you do a build
然后pwnkernel会
and then pwnkernel will go through
构建出所有模块，包括你的模块
build everything including your module
并将其部署到正在运行的内核中（口误）
and deploy it in the running kernel
哦,抱歉
oh sorry
将其部署到一个新的用户空间文件系统中
deploy it in a new user space file system
然后你可以用launch启动内核
where you can then call launch to start the kernel
所有的模块都在这里
and all of the modules are right here
yanmodule.ko在这里
so here's the yanmodule.ko
很棒
awesome stuff okay
我们创建了一个模块
so we've created a module
那么我们如何加载一个模块呢
so how do we load a module
我要展示
so i'm going to show you actually
先关了这个
let's kill the this
我不应该
i shouldn't have
没关系
well it doesn't matter
我们来看看yanmodule是什么
so let's see what yanmodule is
yanmodule
实际就是拷贝了一份hello_log
or really i just copied it from hello_log that module
它是最小的内核模块
it is the smallest possible kernel module
它所做的一切
all it does
哦，我忘了给你们看我的屏幕了
oops i forgot to show you my screen
yanmodule是最小的内核模块
yanmodule is the smallest possible kernel module
其实它就是hello_log
hello_log.c rather
它就往内核日志中打印一条hello
all it does is print to the kernel log hello
还有一条goodbye
and then print goodbye
加载时打印hello
hello is printed when it is loaded
卸载时打印goodbye
goodbye is printed when it is unloaded
我们启动内核
so let's launch the kernel
开始吧
here we go
我们现在在小机器里
we are inside our tiny machine
hello_log在这儿
here is hello_log
如何加载模块
how do you load modules
很容易，用insmod
very easy insmod
实际是init_module系统调用
or realistically the init_module system call
需要文件名等参数
takes a file name and so forth
你可以在man手册上看看
you can look it at the manpage
但这通常是通过insmod完成的
but it's usually done through the insmod utility
当然，你必须有合适权限
of course you have to have the right capabilities
实际上，我们差不多得是root
realisticly we have to be more or less root normally
幸运的是，这个虚拟机中，我们是root
luckily we are root right now in my configuration of this vm
所以我可以执行insmod hello_log
so i can do insmod hello_log
非常简单
and again very simple
它就初始化时打印条日志，退出时打印一条
all it does is log on init log on cleanup
我们开始吧
and here we go
加载完了
i'm loaded it
打出了日志
and it's gives me this log
好的
okay awesome
接下来呢
what's next
列出模块
listing modules
我在视频开始的时候做过
i did this at the beginning of the video
用lsmod
but you can lsmod
能看到它
and we can see that
就加载了它一个
this is the only module i have loaded
还能看到加载位置
and where it's loaded actually
这非常有用
which is very useful
好的，还有什么
okay what else
删除模块
removing modules
能用rmmod删除这个模块
so i can remove this module using rmmod
rmmod hello_log
很有礼貌地跟我说了再见
and says goodbye to me very polite
lsmod看一下，已经不在了
lsmod is no longer there
我可以再insmod一次
i can insmod it again
它又回来了
it's back
我再rmmod一次
and i can rmmod it again
太棒了
awesome
好了，这很简单
all right that was nice and simple
现在我要再花几分钟
now i'm going to take a couple of minutes
演示几个示例模块
and run through a couple of example modules
目前只看了hello_log
we just looked at hello_log
它很简单
it's very simple
内核开发听起来很可怕
again kernel development sounds scary
但你用它，就能写一个模块
but you can write a module with just this
并能让内核执行你的代码
and you have code execution with kernel
太棒了
that's awesome
看看还有什么
let's see what else we got
我们看看hello_dev_char
let's look at hello_dev_char
这创建了一个字符设备文件，我们可以读写它
so this basically just creates a character device file that we can read and write from
我们快速浏览一下
let's take a quick look
它稍微复杂点
it's a little more complicated
你可以看到
so you can see
它有更多的函数
it has a couple of more functions
稍微复杂点
things are a little more complicated
它做的一件事是注册字符设备
one thing that it does is do this register character device
它基本就是
a character device is basically
每次能读取一个字符
just a device that you can read one character at a time from
或几个字符的设备
or however many characters at a time from
相较于块设备
as opposed to a block device
一次要读取特定数量的数据块
where you have to read certain amounts of blocks
块设备，例如有硬盘
a block device is like a hard drive for example
字符设备，有麦克风
a character device is like a microphone
该模块初始化时
when this module is initialized
它注册了一个名为pwn-college-char的字符设备
it registers a character device called pwn college
但该方式注册完，还要在/dev下创建设备文件
but it registers it in a way that we still have to create the device file in /dev
它会告诉我们怎么做
and it'll actually tell us how to do that
当我们调用register_chrdev后
when we call register device
它会返回一个major_number
it receives a major number
这是一个标识符
this is an identifier
有点像文件描述符
kind of like a file descriptor
它是一个数字，表明这是你的设备
in a very different way it is a number that says this is your device
当带有该标识的设备被打开时
when a device with that identifying number is opened
我们的内核模块会被调用
our kernel module will be invoked
它会注册这个file_operations结构体
and then it registers this file operations struct
file_operations有一堆函数指针
file operations struct has a bunch of function pointers
指向read、write、open和release
to read write open and release
打开文件时，调用open
so open gets called when the file is open
关闭文件时，调用release
release gets called when the file is closed
read和write会在文件被读取和写入时调用
read and write gets called when the file is read from or written to
这里我们可以看到非常简单的东西
and here we can see something very very simple here
执行device_read时
we do a device read
打开设备时
when the device is opened
我们就打一条日志，说打开了
all we do is log that it's been open
关闭设备时
when it's closed
打一条日志，说关上了
all we do is log that it's been closed
当设备被读取时
when the device has been being read from
我们返回字符串Hello pwn.college!，然后返回
we just return the string hello pwn college and we return
我们用copy_to_user
we use copy_to_user
copy_to_user是一个内核函数
copy_to_user is a kernel function
能将数据安全地复制到用户空间
that copies data back into user space safely
所以数据
so the data
目标地址就是我们传入的buffer指针
the destination is whatever this buffer pointer that we were passed in
要拷贝的msg
we copy the message
即Hello pwn.college!
hello pwn college
还有长度
and the length
这就是我们输出到用户空间的方式
and this is how we output to the user
他们会读取到的数据
the data that they're going to read
这个驱动程序实际上不支持写入
and this driver doesn't actually support write
它说一下不支持，然后返回错误码EINVAL
it just says it returns an EINVAL error code
这些就是syscall后在rax中拿到的错误码
and these are the error codes that you keep getting in rax from the syscalls
这个错误代码
this error code
这是它输出的长度
this is how much it will have written
我记得copy_to_user会返回还剩多少没输出到用户空间
i think copy_to_user returns how much is left to write out of this amount
如果一次没全输出到用户空间
if it fails to write the whole thing all at once
这就返回它已经输出了多少
and so this returns how much it has written
当然，这需要对齐
of course this needs to line up
否则read会表现得很奇怪
or read will act very strangely
基本上就是这样
so that's basically it
我们insmod hello
let's um insmod hello
哦，在这里
oops it's over here
insmod hello_dev_char
所以它说好的
so it says okay
我们注册的主设备号是248
we registered major number 248
我们创建一个设备文件
let's create a device file
mknod表示make node
mknod is make node
它会创建一个设备文件
it creates a device file
这个c表示是字符设备
and this says character device
这个是该模块分配到的主设备号
and this is the major number that identifier that this module was assigned
在它调用register_chrdev的时候
when it called registered device
在这里
right here
注册字符设备
registered character device
我们运行这个
we run this
现在我们有了一个设备文件
okay now we have a device
我们读它
if we read from this
会得到Hello pwn.college!
we will get hello pwn college
我们这里用head看一下
so let's do head here
Hello pwn.college!
hello pwn college
很酷吧
pretty cool huh
为什么我们有这么多
why do we have a whole bunch of hello pwn colleges
因为head会一直读取，直到它读取了一定行数
because head will keep reading until it reads some amount of lines
这就是head的工作方式
that's what head does
如果用cat
if i've had done cat
会一直卡在这里
we would just be sitting here forever
如果我们只想读一次
if we want to read just once
可以用dd
there's a shell utility dd
它的参数格式很奇怪
it takes a weird argument format if
if，即输入文件，/dev/pwn.college-char
and we have the input files /dev/pwn.college-char
of，即输出文件，/dev/stdout
of /dev/stdout
再给一个读取的字节数
we give it a byte size to read
让它一次读128字节
it'll read a hundred and twenty eight bytes at a time
且只读一次
and to say read only once
和
and
我们的输出在哪里
where's our output
就是这个
there it is
我们输出到文件描述符1
so we've output it to file descriptor one
就好了
and here we go
这就是我们的
so that is our
字符设备
character device
有个类似的proc设备
there's a similar one for a proc device
它不在/dev中
instead of in /dev
我们用proc_create
we use proc_create
这个简单多了
this is much simpler
因为它会自动创建设备文件
because it automatically creates the device
然后它会告诉我们，创建好了
and then it'll tell us that's been created
然后我们可以用完全相同的方式和它互动
and then we can interact with it in exactly the same way
其余的都是一样的
the rest is the same
就是改变了创建的地方
it just changes where it creates it
这是一个不同的模块
it's a different module
我们insmod hello_proc_char
so let's insmod hello_proc_char
怎么了
what's going on
为什么不打印呢?
why didn't print
我们重新启动内核
let's restart the kernel
也许是别的模块有bug
maybe there's some bug in a different module
好了，开始吧
okay here we go
hello_proc_char
好了
there we go
创建了设备文件
it created it
不知道为什么没打印
i don't know why it didn't print
相同的用法
same thing
这里是自动创建的
so here it auto creates it
我们可以读它
and now we can read from it
我们再看一个
let's look at one other one
这是ioctl的交互方式
and that is the ioctl way of interaction
这个有点疯狂
and this one is kind of a little crazier
我们
so we
我们下次演示这个ioctl
actually let's save this ioctl demo
因为要30分钟了
because we're going on to 30 minutes
下一模块演示它
for the next module where i will show it off in
哦,抱歉
oh sorry
下个视频中我将在另一个内核模块中展示它
for the next video where i'll show it off in the context of a different module
这个make_root.c
this make_root.c
它是展示内核漏洞的一个好的方式
that's going to be an awesome way of showing off an actual kernel exploit
不算是一个真正的内核漏洞
or not an actual kernel exploit
算是内核的一个小后门
but a little back door in the kernel
这就是我们关于内核模块的速成课
so that is all for our quick quick crash course into kernel modules
当然
of course
这个模块的练习题中
for the challenge problems in this module
你将主要与内核模块进行交互
you'll mostly be interacting with kernel modules
用它们来帮助你获取模拟器中的flag
trying to use them to help you retrieve a flag inside your emulator
感谢收看
thanks for watching